[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net se radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
software for software engineering radio
this is Robert
blumen I have with me today Lucas gentle
the CEO of Loft Labs Lucas is a maintain
ER of the open source projects
v.com
dev. and devs
space. and he is a speaker at cucon and
other cloud computing conferences Lucas
welcome to software engineering radio
great to be here Robert thanks for
inviting me on the show would you like
to tell the listeners anything else
about your background that I didn't
cover well you mentioned all the open
source projects that I'm a you know
startup founder yeah very deeply
connected to the kubernetes ecosystem to
the open source World maybe one thing
that you haven't mentioned yet I didn't
grow up in the states I grew up in
Germany moved here about like six years
ago or so and uh yeah we're excited to
to talk a little bit more about
specifically our V cluster project today
yeah and I will mention that we have an
international audience of listeners the
show was founded in Germany and Germany
is one of our top listener countries by
percentage so I'm sure many Germans will
be listening to this
podcast today Lucas and I we will be
talking about V clusters we have quite a
lot of content in the archives about
kubernetes clusters that listeners could
listen to to get up to speed on that
including episode 690 on how to set up a
cluster let's not review that let's Dive
Right into kubernetes V clusters what is
a v cluster and how does it differ from
what we call it a base cluster cluster
or a normal cluster what's the term you
use that's not a v cluster I typically
refer to it as a traditional kubernetes
cluster and then the virtual cluster is
something that runs on top of this this
traditional cluster right we also use it
as the the term called host cluster when
you have you know multiple virtual
clusters running on the same cluster
that underlying cluster we we refer to
as the host cluster you know the
difference between the two ultimately is
kubernetes cluster is made out of
machines whether that is bare metal
machines or virtual machines ultimately
it's about how do we schedule containers
across a set of machines right and each
kubernetes cluster has these these
machines attached these nodes right and
some you know Cloud providers allow you
to autoscale your nodes to ultimately
you know add and remove nodes
dynamically depending on how many
containers you have running but you
can't have a dynamic allocation of nodes
to multiple cubern clusters so when you
have two kubernetes clusters and you
have one node you got to put it in
either one of these clusters you can't
share that node across two kubernetes
clust right a virtual cluster uses the
nodes of the underlying cluster so
typically virtual cluster itself doesn't
have any compute nodes right you can
obviously attach dedicated compute nodes
to it if you wish to do so but the big
benefit of it is it uses the noes and
the infrastructure of the underlying
cluster so it's a really great solution
for multi-tenancy if I'm looking at a
kubernetes cluster and I want to share
this cluster that's really hard to do
actually right and that is actually not
obvious because when you're thinking of
kubernetes there's obviously role based
Access Control there's users and groups
right so you'd think it's possible to
share it right there's name spaces and
kubernetes as a unit to separate things
a little bit but again I usually tell
people when you think of a physical
server you also have users and groups
and permissions and folders but it's
still very hard to share a Linux host if
you don't have
virtualization and the same way it's
really hard to share a kubernetes
cluster if you don't have virtualization
for kubernetes and that's ultimately
what V cluster adds on top of a
kubernetes cluster it adds that virtual
layer to give everybody their dedicated
isolated space while still sharing the
underlying cluster and its notes if I
could summarize what you said the key
point about a virtual cluster to
understand what it is is it is a
kubernetes cluster that runs inside of a
host kubernetes
cluster and it does have some of its own
services and then it shares the nodes
with the host was there anything about
that you'd like to correct no that's an
accurate summary that's that's exactly
the idea some things are shared certain
things are completely isolated and
that's the beauty of the virtual cluster
you can mix and match ultimately does
each V cluster have its own isolated
control plane that is correct yes the
virtual cluster ultimately is a
container so in this container you have
a fully fledged kubernetes control plane
that means you have an API server you
have a controller manager you have state
right that state can live in a sqlite
database or in a full-blown ETD cluster
right like a real kubernetes cluster
would be using the only thing that it
doesn't have which a regular kubernetes
cluster has in its control plane is a
scheduler because the underlying cluster
has a schedul and the Schuler
distributes the ODS to the different
nodes the virtual cluster typically
doesn't have any noes or may just have
some optional nodes attached to it but
usually it uses the underlying cluster
scheduler to actually get containers
launched on the specific VMS of the host
cluster I heard you correctly you said
the vcl cluster control plane is a
container did you mean a single
container or does each piece of the
control plane have its own
container yeah it's actually one part
and and a couple of containers in the
part that's correct in a control plane
if you're on a large enough traditional
cluster you might scale out different
parts of the control plane differently
like you might have three or five
instances of etcd for high availability
and you might scale your API
server horizontally if you are putting
your entire control plane in one one pod
do you have to decide up
front what size of resource you give to
each piece and you're that's pretty much
fixed for the duration of the V cluster
yeah so we actually do something really
interesting so when you look at the
multiple parts of the control plane so
there's one part that contains pretty
much all the core components right so
controller manager and API server we
actually bake them in a single container
but then you have things for example for
the DNS like core DNS we have two
options to have it baked in or to run it
separately as a separate container even
as a separate part right to be launched
and that way you have that flexibility
of what do you want to run baked in and
what do you want to run separately
typically to run things separately makes
a little bit heavier weight right and
running them embedded which is our
default typically uh makes it much more
lightweight the same counts for the data
store so one thing we do for example is
when you spin up a v cluster you just go
to V cluster.com right now and run the
quick start right you download the CLI
we have this command called V cluster
create in the CLI that helps you spin up
a v cluster It ultimately just sets a
couple of config options and then runs a
Helm install it's nothing more than that
but it spins up a a virtual cluster in
the most lightweight form cuz we know
people who just want to get started
right want to see the the the wow effect
right and there's a lot of things that
can go wrong if you want to spin up a
fully fledged ETD cluster right so what
we do instead is we even bake in the
data store so for example the data store
is just a sqlite in a persistent volume
right and you could even disable the
persistent volume and it would be
entirely ephemeral right you restart the
container the cluster is completely
reset right and so the V cluster is
pretty Dynamic it can be as and as
lightweight as you want it to be also on
the Other Extreme to be as heavyweight
as you want it right and you can
horizontally scale pretty much each
component of the V cluster pretty easily
so it's really depending on your use
case and how much resilience and
separate scalability for each component
you actually need for that particular
scenario that you're running the vust I
want to highlight one aspect of what you
just said if you want want the Fe
cluster to be durable you need to make
some arrangement for it to access a
persistent volume for the persistence
piece anything you'd like to expand on
that no absolutely if your kubernetes
cluster has persistent volume claim
provisioning enabled like Dynamic
provisioning of persistent volumes um
that is what we're using by default
right so we look into the cluster when
you run V cluster create and actually
see hey is that possible right uh and
then reprovision the PV that way which
is obviously super straightforward most
kubernetes clusters even like Docker
desktop and mini cube right have that
either by default enabled or let you
enable that with just a single CLI
command or a click in the docker desktop
UI but obviously you know when you're uh
in Cloud environments sometimes
regulated Industries don't want Dynamic
provisioning every PV needs to manually
get provisioned right hopefully you
don't have to be in that strict of an
environment but if you are then you can
also specify these things via the the
values yaml right we call it V cluster
yaml which is essentially the Central
File where you have all the config
options available to you and then you
can you can apply that with your V
cluster create command or with the helm
install command you have up to this
point mentioned most of the pieces of
the control plane but not the networking
does the V cluster share in the post
clusters networking or does run its own
network so we regards to the networking
the virtual cluster uses the underlying
clusters networking that's because the
underlying clusters nodes are being used
and that's obviously where most of the
networking is happening other than you
know DNS right DNS is actually something
that we run as I mentioned earlier as
part of the control plan of the virtual
cluster right so there's a there's a
separate DNS for each V cluster which
makes sense because things in a in DNS
are based on the names of your name
spaces right
and if you have three virtual clusters
and they all have a nam space called
database you would have conflicts if you
were to use you would try to map that to
the underlying DNS that's why every V
cluster gets its own DNS but when you
actually look at the IP addresses and
the network traffic between containers
or from the internet to a container or
from a container to the internet right
or within your VPC all of that runs on
the nodes and on the network that your
actual kubernetes clust your host
cluster is a is a part of are there any
best practices about how you launch
these in the name spaces of the host
cluster does each V cluster get its own
name space or how do you do that yeah so
you can have multiple V clusters in the
same Nam space but we typically
encourage people to have one V cluster
per namespace that's definitely best
practice we encourage and mostly the
reason for this is every part that gets
launched inside the V cluster let's say
the V cluster has 20 name spaces right
what typically happens is we got to
translate the names of these parts down
to the host cluster because the pods get
actually launched by the host cluster
and the way that works is we copy them
into the namespace where the virtual
cluster runs so if I have 100 Parts in
these 20 name spaces and I look into the
host cluster I see one name space where
the V cluster is running with the V
cluster pod for the control plan plus I
see these 100 parts right that come from
the V cluster all in that very same name
space so if you have multiple V clusters
in there it's much more difficult to get
an overview of what belongs to which V
cluster we obviously you know we have
some prefixes and suffixes Etc to to
make it more clear and understandable we
set labels as well in this process right
to make it you know filterable Etc but
it's just so much easier if you split up
by namespace and the edit benefit is
also if you're introducing things like
Network policy
or you're using things like cavano or
open policy agent right I know you had a
a session with Jim the other day right
about cavano and and and policies and
kubernetes it's very very important to
set these policies on a namespace level
because a lot of these constructs in
kubernetes are designed to be used at
the namespace level you can use it with
labels as well but the chance that
you're going to make a mistake is going
to be much much higher so we typically
recommend do all of this on a namespace
level and one V cluster per
namespace okay now you did mention that
this is a great solution for
multi-tenancy I can think of at least
two other ways you might handle that one
would be to put each tenant in its own
namespace another would be to give each
tenant their own kubernetes cluster
could you give us some pros and cons of
these different
approaches yeah absolutely let's start
with the Nam spaces right if you give
every tenant a nam space I mean in a way
with a V cluster as I just said right
every V cluster should run in separate
namespace so in a way you're kind of
doing that already with your tenants
right the benefit of having the V
cluster layer on top rather than giving
tenants directly the name space lies in
giving the tenants the autonomy that
they actually need if you are restricted
to a single namespace in kubernetes it's
kind of like if I gave you just a single
folder on a shared Linux host and you
had minimal permissions to do anything
right so if you don't have root access
to that machine and you can't install
anything in this Debian system or
something like that right then you're
going to be very very limited right and
every tenant will now need to agree on
certain things we actually had a lot of
this going on like in the you know late
'90s and the first like kind of Internet
wave where people had these like folders
web space sharing right where hosters
were essentially giving you these
limited capabilities to host your little
website but everybody had to agree on
what PHP version or something is running
on these servers right with
virtualization everybody can roll their
own and they have a lot more freedom you
feel like you got a full-blown server
and that autonomy is really important
for engineers to do their work and to
move fast right when you give somebody
in namespace you're going to be super
limited similarly limited one of the
most pressing limitations is cluster
wide objects in kubernetes for example
crds custom resource definitions right
are things that allow you to extend
kubernetes and when you look at most
Helm charts out there and and most tools
designed for kubernetes you know take
some of the popular ones like sto Argo
CD all of these tools introduce their
custom CDs and many companies are
building their own custom crds they may
have a crd for back end and front end
and when they're building these crds
crds are operated at a cluster wide
level so there's no way for two tenants
to work on the same crd in the same
cluster and not getting each other's way
it's not possible to constrain them to
just a nam space another option maybe
you know let's say you want to another
you know scenario where you're really
limited maybe if you architecting your
application to run across three
namespaces if you just get a single one
or I give you three isolated ones and
they can't communicate each other
because you set up Network policies as
you should right as a cluster admin who
wants to keep tenants apart well now you
as an engineer can't architect your
application the way you wish to
architect it it's very very limiting so
that's the benefit of the V cluster you
really are still in a single name space
but it doesn't feel like it for you you
actually have multiple name space you
have cluster right objects you could
even choose a different kubernetes
version right each of these we classes
can have a separate version they don't
need to be all the same they don't need
to be the same as the host cluster right
and that gives tenants a lot of
freedom and then compare to that that to
having separate clusters which obviously
gives you the ultimate freedom but it
comes at a very Hefty price so if you
were to provision a th clusters for a
th000 engineers in your organization
that's a pretty hefty CL provider Bill
and a lot of our customers like
commercial customers that work with us
the the large Enterprise the fortune
500s of the world they have hundreds or
even thousands of clusters and that's a
really big burden on these operational
teams it's not just the cost for the
computer it's also the cost for
upgrading things keeping things in in
sync you need Fleet Management suddenly
for that large Fleet of clusters it's a
really complicated operation to maintain
500 or a thousand plus kubernetes
clusters and with with virtual clusters
it is much much cheaper and becomes much
easier because when you think of it you
can now you know run an ISO in the host
cluster and you can share it across 500
virtual clusters so instead of
maintaining 500 esos you have to
maintain one and you may not even need
automation for that one I would still
recommend automating it right and using
things like gith ups and infrastructures
code Etc but you know the burden becomes
becomes much much lower in the the
amount of code and plumbing you need to
write around things the inconsistencies
you have between systems right become
much much smaller when you have fewer
host clusters and have virtual clusters
instead and then the as I said the the
cost is much much lower as well compared
to running 500 separate clusters just
think about 500 clusters with three
notes each right we have 1,500 noes
running most of them are going to be
idle especially if you're thinking
pre-production clusters right most of
them are going to run idle most of the
time in a virtual cluster you may get
away with having 500 noes for everybody
because they're much higher utilized
right and much more dynamically
allocated across your
tenants you raised a lot of points there
there is one thing that I ran across in
some of the research that you haven't
mentioned I'll ask you about this the
time to spin up what is the advantage of
V clusters in that area oh yeah that's a
that's sometimes I overlook but yeah
it's it's a big one V cluster spins up
in like you know six seven seconds like
super super quick right depends a little
bit on your configuration maybe the
heavier ones take 10 seconds right but
it's in in that direction versus if you
were to spin up one of the easiest to
spin up clusters today which are like
eks or GK or AKs right public Cloud they
streamlined everything for us still
these clusters take about like 30 40
minutes to start right that's obviously
a big difference and that you know that
short start time also allows us to
dynamically turn virtual clusters on and
off when they're not being used if that
would take 40 minutes to launch a real
cluster that is not something you do
three times a day up and down right but
if it takes six seconds and you're going
to go for your lunch break for 45
minutes or an hour so we can turn the
virtual cluster off while you're not
using it and that's actually part of our
commercial offering we call that sleep
mode it's something that monitors the
network traffic to your virtual cluster
and turns it off when you're not using
it and the cool thing is it also turns
it on again when you start using it
again so let's say you run cubec I get
pods that request comes in and that
request hits the network of the host
cluster first right the load balancer
there and we halt it there because we
see oh the virtual cluster is asleep
then we wake it up real quick which is
just launching the control plane which
is just a container right starting
container super quick and then we let
the request through that means that
request after you got your lunch or over
the weekend Monday morning that first
request may take like five or six
seconds instead of 500 milliseconds but
the company saved a lot of money in the
time you actually didn't use this
cluster right and that is very very
beneficial for a lot of companies I
understand that the turn on off the
merits of that can you think of any
other examples where it enables you to
do something you or a client or customer
to do something because of the fast spin
up time that they could not do if it was
minutes yeah when you think of a
scenario and we've had a couple of
startups do this right a cluster per
customer so let's say your application
launches pods let's say you have
something like a a batch job framework
that spins up a pod every time a
customer clicks a button in the UI or
hits an API request you kind of need to
give everybody their own cluster to keep
them separate but spinning up a cluster
would take 45 minutes so you're
automatically going to default to having
a product where you see you go to the
website and it's like a get a demo and
it's going to take a while to get access
to the product because somebody's got to
spin up a eks cluster behind the scenes
and launch that product in there we have
some customers and we actually gave a
demo with with a a smaller startup at
ccon last year about this where they
were demonstrating hey we wanted to have
a a demo environment on our website
launchable for customers immediately so
when you go to their website and you hit
the sign up now link and you type in
your email address it's going to tell
you spinning up your environment and
that spinner is going to go on for 10
seconds and then it's going to drop you
into that product what happens behind
the scenes is a virtual cluster gets
launched then the application gets
deployed to the virtual cluster and then
once that is ready you get dropped into
the UI and that's a beautiful experience
for for customer right you get your
hands on the product immediately right
and then the other benefit that they're
using is for these trial customers that
just sign up and try things out in the
free tier right they're actually also
using the sleep mode to turn their
product off and you're not using it and
that's just things that is unimaginable
with real kubernetes clusters right
because no it's got to be provision and
deprovision and a whole bunch of other
things need to happen right with the
virtual cluster and its kind of dynamic
nature right spinning up so quickly and
you know turn off so quickly these these
scenarios become possible I could
definitely see that you could give a
demo in a minute rather than an hour as
being a big product feature I want to
reflect on another point you raised
about large company and it has a th000
kubernetes clusters I recognize that
this number a thousand is a number you
picked out for the purpose of examples
let's say that this organization now
learns about V clusters are they going
to have one kubernetes cluster with a
thousand V clusters or how what's the
condensation factor that you would get
and what is now the Criterion for
deciding how many traditional clusters
you need and than the multiplier on V
clusters per traditional cluster yeah
that's an excellent question I remember
the early days of the Container Wars
right and I think mesosphere had this
goal with dcos where they wanted to
built this like giant machine is I think
how they called it right so essentially
wiring everything up to be one giant
machine that you throw things at that
that sounds amazing right I think with
kubernetes and the way currently things
are set up especially in the most
sophisticated systems even like the
public clouds right you still pretty
much have Regional kues clusters because
of latency reasons right it's it's
really tough to run such a you know even
though it's a distributed system the
reconciliation Loop in kubernetes and
there's just a lot of networking going
on right if you were to split that up
across the entire world and build one
giant cluster right like I mean again
like that's not really possible in any
of the cloud providers today but I'm not
sure if if that is even a desirable path
to be honest I think what we see most
people do is not have one giant cluster
but have a handful of very large
clusters so instead of having 500
clusters across four cloud provider
regions you may get by by having four
clusters in four cloud provider regions
or maybe you're saying okay we do want
to keep prod and pre-o completely
separate so you may have eight clusters
but not 500 right and I think that that
reduction by you know factor of like 10
20 30 right that is what we're looking
for but we're not looking for going from
500 to one I think that would be very
extreme for most Enterprises out there
but it is certainly feasible for smaller
companies if you're a startup and you're
currently running 10 kubernetes clusters
I bet you will get away with one or
maybe
two are the V clusters assigned a fixed
amount of resources such as memory cores
and storage space or are they somewhat
elastic very elastic or they can grow as
needed based on
workload yeah that's actually
interesting right cuz uh thinking of the
analogy to virtu machines typically
virtual machines you pre-provision you
assign a certain amount of memory to to
a specific virtual machine right a
virtual cluster it's much more elastic
and and dynamic by default so by default
we're just using the underly Clusters
node and whatever whatever resources are
available on these nodes and if you
launch a thousand Parts in your virtual
cluster and your underlying cluster only
has two nodes but Autos scaling enabled
you'll see that number of nodes in the
host cluster go up and that's kind of
the beauty of kubernetes and the
elasticity that you get in the cloud but
what you can also do in the v cluster
you can obviously restrict the amount of
resources that should be allowed to to
be consumed by that virtual cluster and
you can you you can also Reserve certain
things for a virtual cluster but again
by default it starts like completely
Dynamic right that's typically where
we're coming from and then you're
optimizing towards like okay let me set
limits and you know we do obviously
recommend setting limits for certain
things to to ensure that one of your
tenants is not going completely Rogue
and putting a lot of strain on that
cluster or taking all the resources away
especially if you don't have a cluster
that order scales you're in the private
cloud or you don't have an order scale
enabled right you obviously need to
manage who consumes these resources to
ensure a certain you know fairness
amongst your tenants do you have any
stories that revolve around multi-tenant
system where the tenants either did or
did not have resource constraints on the
V clusters and what happened
it's certainly the case when I think
when you're thinking about sqlite for
example as the backing store for a v
cluster we had a whole bunch and we
started with with k3s as the default
this so in the v cluster you can run
multiple multiple dis as well vanilla
kubernetes k0s k3s we started with k3s
and with sqlite as a default which is a
very very lightweight setup and then we
saw a couple of people really excited
about V cluster who who put us in
production right away within the first
year of launching to open source right
Really Brave Pioneers right I probably
wouldn't have there to put V production
at this point now obviously for sure
it's possible but three years ago that
was a little bit of a scary thought and
we saw a couple of coupon talks and
people going out there and saying like
yeah hey we have these 80 virtual
clusters in production and our customers
running these virtual clusters right and
we we were always seeking out these
people obviously for their experiences
for their stories but also to make make
sure that they know us and know who to
call because you know we appreciated
them pioneering putting vust in
production and there's one particular
incident and they became a not going to
disclose the name obviously but they
became a paying customer later on and
they are running over 400 kubernetes
virtual clusters today but back then
they had like maybe 50 40 50 and they
were running them with sqlite and then
they hit us up at one point and we're
like our biggest customer which
obviously has the biggest load on their
virtual cluster is really seeing a
degraded performance in their virtual
cluster and then we asked them how set
up and like can you explain a little bit
more and they were like yeah it's all
like the standard the default and like
oh wow so it's site right it's a single
file database so no wonder that
performance is going to get degraded as
more API requests come into that
kubernetes API and then we help them
actually you know we have a feature
called embedded at CD which converts the
sqlite into to an ETD cluster that runs
inside the part of the V cluster and is
horizontally scalable with the number of
parts that you give to this V cluster
and that's a beautiful way for them to
go from seite which is not scalable at
all to a one note ETD cluster and then
to scale it to multinode ETD cluster and
they started rolling that out to
actually solve these problems it's a
yeah it's it's it's pretty fascinating
but we've seen these kind of War
Stories we've talked quite a lot about
the architecture of the V cluster what
parts are shared parts are not and then
you also mention that it's deployed with
a Helm chart part we haven't covered is
e cluster is a kubernetes Operator
Operator is not something we've covered
yet on S maybe we could start with the
backgrounder on what is a kubernetes
operator yeah so kubernetes operators
control you know essentially the object
that get created from Custom resource
definitions in kubernetes so in
kubernetes you really describe your
desired State and then the cluster
figures out how to get there what
changes need to be made to your
infrastructure to your configuration to
your containers right in order to
achieve that desired State there's a lot
of controllers in kubernetes that's the
central piece of an operator right like
the replica controller for example you
say I want three replicas of this part
which is a statement and then the
replica controller has to create three
pods right and that achieves your
desired state right and operators and
controllers and kubernetes do the same
thing typically when you write them you
add custom resources to kubernetes and
then you describe what the desired state
of these these resources should be and
then a particular controller essentially
achieves that state for V cluster is
actually when you look at our simplest
way completely in the open source
project there's actually no operator
involved it's really just a hel chart
that creates a stateful set or
deployment with the V cluster part
definition inside of it and the regular
you know kubernetes you know replica
controller Etc takes care of it but in
our commercial product we obviously have
an operator and we have a crd for
virtual clusters Etc which makes it
easier to describe that desired state
right do you want a virtual cluster with
at CD backing or connected to an RDS
database to storage stay there so you
don't have to worry about backing an ETD
cluster up and those kind of things it
makes makes it much much easier if you
have a large Fleet of virtual clusters
and one interesting thing we do as well
because we acknowledg a lot of people
start with virtual clusters in the open
source and they basically do the helm
install right no crds involved just in a
single name space Here's a deployment
here's stateful set Etc we have a way to
we call it externally deployed virtual
clusters we actually just announced that
last week it's a very new feature and
this feature allows you to add these
open-source virtual clusters to the
control plan plan to actually create the
the crds so a little bit the other way
around I have a state and then I create
the desired State and then obviously
they immediately match once that happens
the last part I did not understand so
could you go through that again a bit
slower and I'll try to ask questions
along the way if I don't get it yeah
absolutely so if you have 100 virtual
clusters today and you just deployed
them with the helm chart right so you
just have 100 stateful sets that create
100 virtual cluster parts right you have
no crd called virtual cluster involved
yet but you want it because you want to
make that move to the commercial product
because of all the benefits you get
there like sleep mode the Fleet
Management you want to use the UI to
manage the virtual clusters right what
you can do now with this feature called
externally deployed virtual clusters
which we you know added in the newest
version of our platform then you can
essentially point the platform at these
100 virtual clusters and they kind of
get imported and what we what we do is
we create the custom resources based on
the what's already in your cluster
typically in kubernetes the loop works
the other way around it's kind of like
here's my desired State and then turn it
into what actually happens in the
cluster we kind of do it the other way
around just to make it easier for people
that come entirely from the open source
to explore the commercial option as well
I got it then the migration path is from
the non-operator version to the operator
version sort of like doing a terraform
import something like that exactly
that's exactly that's a Perfect Analogy
yes since it's possible to do this I
would guess there are other people who
figured out the same Principle as Loft
labs are there other vendors in this
space or other open- source projects in
the general space of running kubernetes
on
kubernetes yes definitely so when we
actually got started one of The
Inspirations for V cluster was a project
called
k3v which is what Darren Shepard the CTO
and founder of Rancher put on I think it
was like a a weekend project right put
it on GitHub and said like this is how
you could put k3s into the Pod and run
it on top of another kubernetes cluster
right and then we saw that and we were
like what about if we took this all the
way right I think he went 1% of the way
and we're like What if he went all the
way and and programmed all the rest that
is necessary this project at that time
was about a year old I think it wasn't
really working anymore unfortunately but
the idea was fascinating and I think
other people got started around the same
time too there was an effort as part of
the multi-tenancy working group in
kubernetes they built something called
hierarchical name spaces in kubernetes
and they also built something that they
called cluster API nested as part of
cluster API and both of these efforts
show exactly the same need right you
have multiple tenants they need multiple
name spaces how do you arrange that
right I think neither of these projects
are super active anymore at this point
but there have been other efforts coming
up so for example redhead launched a
project that they call hosted control
planes where they run a control plan
inside a container so it's essentially
kubernetes in kubernetes as well right
but what is different than you know
there's kamaji which is pretty similar
to host a control plan it's another open
source project also launches a
kubernetes control in a container but
what none of them do is essentially
reuse the underlying host clusters nodes
so any of these control ples you're
launching you will have to attach
dedicated noes to them versus with the
virtual cluster you do not have to do
that because we swap out the scheduler
with our own component we call it the
Synchro and what the syncher does is it
doesn't schedule to nodes like a regular
scheduler would do so it doesn't need to
know nodes instead it's synch izes the
state of a pod from a virtual cluster
into the host cluster and the status for
example image pullback off and any kind
of events Etc it sys those pieces of
information back into the virtual
cluster that's what the Synchro does and
that's really the I guess the magic
source and the the really great idea
about about V cluster um that nobody
else is pursuing everybody else you know
runs a control plane inside a part and
then has as you attach notes to that
whole plan dedicated noes right which is
still a great benefit because you don't
have to you know run so many control
planes you save a lot of nodes just for
control planes or you save a lot of like
there's a fee attached to spinning up a
cluster in a public Cloud right you save
a lot of that headache right with this
approach which is great and especially
in the private cloud is a huge step
forward right where you don't have so
many dedicated control plane nodes
available you have one control plane
cluster with a couple of nodes and then
you have all your worker nodes that are
separate but with the V cluster we take
it one step further so I would say use
case wise we're you you know really
optimized for that multi-tenancy inside
a shared truly shared cluster rather
than just hosting control points in the
model where you attach the nodes to the
kubernetes V cluster cluster within a
cluster then did I understand you would
run a scheduler Within
the nested cluster and it would schedule
on the attached
nodes yes that is true so what we do is
the Sinker essentially would take care
of so that you can essentially tell us
should this part end up on your regular
sync uh flow where it goes down to your
host cluster and then your host clusters
scheduler would take care of scheduling
it to a node or you can say hey this
particular part I want that to be on one
of my dedicated nodes and then a
scheduler would schedule it so in that
case you actually have a scheduler and a
sinker running in the same virtual
clust okay you did say earlier that you
optionally may attach nodes to the V
cluster in your model but it's not
required as it is in some other
product yeah that's correct it's for
that scenario right so you have either I
think there's three modes right it's
either completely separate nodes for
each control plan that is what kamaji
Hoster control plane Etc allow you in a
regular kubernetes cluster frankly as
well right dedicated nodes right and
then you have the Other Extreme
completely shared nodes which is what
the V cluster does by default with the
Syer where the pods just get synced and
the underlying cluster takes care of and
then the V Custer allows you this
beautiful thing in the middle as well
which is this little bit of a hybrid
approach to say like hey this is what I
want dedicated and this is what I want
uh
Shar okay and then the SEC if I
understand it observes the scheduling
that is taking place on the host cluster
and subscribes or receives events or in
some other way understands where it's
been scheduled so then it could provide
that information back to the control
plane of the nested cluster which needs
to know where the service is
running that is correct yes so the
virtual cluster essentially monitors the
underlying part and you know in
kubernetes there's typically two parts
of an object that or maybe three right
there's the metadata right which is the
thing I first forgot and then there's
the spec where you describe your desired
State and then there's a status which
typically the controllers use to write
down things like which note did this all
get scheduled on and was the container
successfully started or that's where you
also see the relation to events in
kubernetes right every time a container
starts or container crashes or something
gets rescheduled kubernetes and and a
lot of other controllers do that too we
do that too in our commercial product
you emit events right so we also
subscribe to the events that get emitted
for that particular part right and that
way we can essentially import these
things into the virtual cluster again so
that you get the observability because
let's think of the scenario I'm
launching a part and you have the
classical scenario image pullback up
because you didn't give it like the
credentials to your private registry or
something like that right or you mistype
them or you know anything went wrong in
that process right then you need to see
that that image couldn't be pulled right
and you also need to see once that
container may be started but then
crashes five minutes later because I
don't know it could be a om kill or
something like that right it has a
memory leak right like there's so many
things could happen you just need to be
able to see that in the virtual cluster
the same way as you see it as if you had
your own cluster that's overall our goal
we essentially want to make sure that
when you know an organization or a
platform team hands out virtual clusters
to their tenants that these tenants
don't even realize that they gotten a
virtual cluster same way as if I give
you a ec2 instance you may not even
realize you don't have a bare metal
server right that transition should be
relatively seamless unless you do
something very very specific deep down
with the hardware for that 1% Edge case
then you definitely notice but 99% of
cases you won't notice are you in a VM
or you a actual physical server the same
counts for virtual cluster and that's
where we're also aiming to with every
release we're doing we're passing the
cncf perance tests for kubernetes that
means we're certified kubernetes drro
and that's very important for us to be
able to communicate that to our user
base right because that creates a lot of
trust hey I can point my CI pipeline
that was previously pointed to deploy to
a real cluster I can now point it to a
virtual cluster and nothing breaks and
that is the goal you shouldn't have to
re architect your application because
you're Now using a virtual I have read
that the thing which constrains how
large a kubernetes cluster can get is at
CD everything else is pretty much
stateless but ET CD has a single leader
and All rights have to go through the
leader you can only write so fast onto a
storage device so that ends up being the
thing which constrains how big a cluster
can get I read something while I was
researching this episode that said this
may be helped by V clusters is because
you may be able to offload some of the
rights onto the storage
of the V cluster but now in light of our
past few minutes discussion about how
some of the activity is actually done on
the host cluster what is your view on
whether these V clusters can truly
increase the scale of a host
cluster that's awesome question yeah
when you when you talk about a large
kubernetes cluster definitely right the
API server the ETD right there's so many
many things that are under heavy load at
a certain point and I think when you
think of the virtual cluster you know
the the load is now first on the virtual
cluster right instead of the underlying
host cluster the beauty of that is you
know thep the syncing that happens the
syncing happens only where it's
necessary so let's say you have a lot of
controllers and a lot of crds think of a
crd think of a controller like C manager
that Provisions certificates does that
launch pods does that need networking
not really it is a lot of objects a lot
of certificate objects and Certificate
request objects and you know all of
these objects and all of these objects
and there's so many requests going to
the kubernetes API by that controller
watcher right every time a certificate
gets created or deleted something
happens in the kubernetes API but we
don't sync any of that that stays within
your virtual
cluster only when you launch a c where
we actually say a container needs to be
launched on a node that's when we need
to use the Synchro and the beauty is
most of the requests in a kubernetes
cluster are not part related requests
even when you think of what created that
part well what created that part is
first let's say a deployment replica
number of four so what happens is first
you have a cube C request to create that
deployment and then you have the the
controller manager now creating four
parts which is four more requests and
then you actually have the launching of
these parts for us we only have to
launch parts so you're saving to create
the deployment and you know a lot of
other things that are higher level
resources in compies all the crds a lot
of crds right ultimately create a part
but what happens beforehand that crd
interaction Etc that doesn't need to be
synced just a part needs to be synced
and kept ins sync that means the
underlying cluster is going to have a
lot fewer requests and de facto you're
right that actually leads to an
defective sharding of the kubernetes
cluster and actually makes the cluster
more scalable than it would be without
that layer of you know the virtual
cluster on top would the V cluster
typically take as much trouble to be
highly available as the host cluster and
if you lose a v cluster you have your
persistence can you recover it
straightforwardly yeah I think we got a
a differentiate between the public and
private Cloud here if you're in a
private Cloud you have obviously a lot
more responsibilities on your own but if
you're in the public Cloud you have it
much much easier with a V cluster where
you can essentially say hey let me make
this V cluster highly available by
offloading its state to something like a
RDS in AWS or any kind of like hosted
MySQL or postgress database so you don't
even need to use an N CD cluster that
you kind of spin up yourself right or
you don't need to use like sqlite or
eded ATD which is also something you
need to back up right but if you put it
in rdds well AWS is going to maintain
that for you make that super highly
scalable and to your point earlier about
the giant machine across the word right
in terms of like having just one
kubernetes cluster the beauty of using
things like glob RDS CU like Global
databases is pretty much a thing already
in Cloud providers if you're using
Global RDS as a storage back end for a v
cluster you can move a v cluster from
one cluster to another cluster which is
actually really interesting for things
like failover scenarios right the only
thing admittedly I have to mention here
is the persistent volumes they still
live in that cluster so if you have
anything that has really like persistent
volumes attached that are really
important and not just just you know get
created for caching or other reasons
right then that can be recreated right
sometimes persistent volumes are just to
survive container restarts for a certain
amount of state but if you have really
important state that cannot be recreated
then obviously that's a separate
migration process however we actually
working on something we call that
snapshotting a euster kind of like
snapshotting of VM which will even let
you allow to snapshot the persistent
volumes that are attached to Cluster
it's a it's a pretty interesting model
you now if we're talking about the
private Cloud then ha and resilience for
real clusters obviously is a huge burom
for people and for V clusters it may
make it a little bit easier because you
have fewer of these real clusters to
manage but you have to worry about the
state of these V cluster and we do help
you with our commercial Solutions and if
you do have ways to uh use managed
databases or you know you're much more
comfortable with running like my SQL and
post databases Etc then like relational
databases than you are with maintaining
and running an ETD cluster which
admittedly a lot of people are because
we've been doing like relational
databases since forever I feel like
right so a lot of it teams have really
resilient Frameworks for running
relation relational databases then it
actually becomes a lot easier than
running a real
cluster one other area before we reach
end of time I was unclear on while
researching this is if in a V cluster
you want to run a workload and put it on
the public
internet I understand from our earlier
discussion that the V cluster does share
the host clusters Network so would you
have to add now an Ingress object and
whatever other networking resources to
get from the host cluster to the public
internet or what's the what are the
building blocks to get the V cluster
service to be on the public internet
yeah there's roughly two routes and it's
the same two routes as pretty much with
any other crd and controller for example
in kubernetes you can always say I want
this entirely separate for the entire V
cluster or I want this shared with other
V clusters so if you run let's say you
want it completely inside the V cluster
and you want to create an Ingress right
then you can essentially launch an
Ingress controller inside the virtual
cluster now I do have to mention that
would mean you have to allow the V
cluster to provision load balancer which
is sometimes not desired because each
load balance has a certain fee attached
to it right but then you have
essentially your engine X running for
that V cluster separately and now you
can create ingresses in the v cluster
right however the more popular approach
is actually we call that shared platform
stack certain components you want to run
in the host cluster like for example an
Ingress controller maybe an sto right
service measures very very popular one
obviously maybe something like open
policy agent as well right like a lot of
like security monitoring logging
Prometheus for example right where
you're saying hey this should be used
across all
vers that means you can run it in the
host cluster and what you can enable in
the v cluster config similar to pot
syncing you can enable syncing for that
particular Resource as well so let's say
you want to sync ingresses because you
want to have engine X Ingress controller
and maybe CT manager run in the
underlying cluster so you get automatic
certificate provisioning you
automatically have ingresses in the
underlying cluster only thing you need
to tell the V cluster is make it easier
for your tenants right to selfs serve
your tenants you allow them to sync
ingresses that means when a tenant
creates an Ingress that Ingress gets
synced down similar to a pod right and
then the underlying clusters engine X
Ingress controller is going to handle
that Ingress and the search manager is
going to add a certificate for it Etc
and you'll see all of that status back
in the virtual cluster and that's how
you would expose the virtual clusters
you know Services running inside the V
cluster to the public internet and
obviously that saves a lot of resources
a lot of load balancer resources Etc
compared to running separate clusters
and having 500 separate load balancers
and engine X Ingress controllers running
Etc and you can Again mix and match so
let's say say for 499 of your vclasses
totally fine to use a shared one but
then one of your teams wants to test the
bleeding edge version of engine X you'll
allow them to provision one load
balancer and they run their own Ingress
controller that's really the Bea beauty
of it you can mix and match these
approaches I get that you have a lot of
flexibility and the more that you share
things across 500 V clusters you have
resource savings In fairness I suggest
that would reduce the benefit of
isolation which is one of the one of the
benefits of V clusters is the more that
you share the less isolation you have is
that fair yeah I would say that's
definitely fair yeah if you start with a
V cluster and you for example say we
have shared nodes completely all of the
nodes are completely shared right there
is things like container breakouts that
you have to think about right and that
may be totally okay for you know
preproduction and test and Dev
environment it's very unlik likely that
there's a malicious actor everything is
behind your VPC right within your
company's Network and it may be totally
okay to share a note but when you're
thinking about production instances you
may want to actually give your customers
dedicated noes or specific dedicated
controllers there's obviously an
evaluation that has to be done for each
individual use case and for each
individual controller and what you want
to share and what you don't you know
with regards to the nodes that's a
question we get a lot right for these
production scenarios there is things you
can do though right there's Technologies
like cutter containers and firecracker
Etc technologies that let you provision
micro VMS or essentially more hardened
containers to make it much easier to go
with this shared model or even things
like you know you can run gke autopilot
where you don't even see any notes
anymore right or you can run eks on top
of fargate which is an option that you
know people don't even know about
sometimes right and you could say this
farget PA is great for hosting our
application but then we're going to you
know launch pods from there in another
kubernetes cluster that essentially has
regular nodes right so there's a lot of
flexibility and it really depends on
your particular use case but you're
definitely right the more you share the
blurrier the lines get in terms of
isolation of course we're close to end
of time were there any key takeaways
about V clusters we haven't covered that
you want the listeners to know about I
would say just try it out it's really
easy to get started with I think
sometimes you know we we talk about very
complex things in this show Robert I
think you you asked some really good
questions we went pretty deep on a lot
of topics but you know anyone who's
listening to this don't let that scare
you off to get started with it is really
easy you download the CLI you run V
cluster create and it spins up a virtual
cluster in in a namespace of you know
your Docker desktop cluster or your mini
Cube or whatever you have running
locally and suddenly you can spin up 20
virtual clusters you have 20 clusters
running now in your local home lab right
something that probably wasn't possible
beforehand right you can group things by
project you can run one per pull request
as a preview environment right there's
so many interesting things you can do
with v cluster and the barrier to entry
to start it is really easy it's
completely open source it takes one
command to spin one up and it takes as
we said earlier like six seven seconds
for it to be ready so yeah you can
obviously dive very very deep into the
architecture and the underlying INF
structure and I encourage everybody to
look at the docs if they want to know
the specifics of any of these topics but
yeah to get started is super easy and
maybe one more shout out if you're
interested in joining the community we
have a slack Community with about like
3,500 members so just head to V
cluster.com and hit the join us on
select button and uh yeah hope to see a
lot of you
there Lucas would you like to point
listeners anywhere on the internet to
either you or Loft labs
yeah you can definitely find me on on
LinkedIn on X and the usual social media
channels uh feel free to connect I'm
pretty approachable right I get back to
everybody where I try to and uh yeah
just reach out other than that obviously
you find the open source project and
also our other open source projects
definitely worth checking out defp pod
for example as well a project that we
launched last year very popular it's
like a GitHub Cod spaces alternative if
you want to run something that code
spaces but you want to maybe run it with
Git lab or you want to run it in your
private Cloud right or you want to run
it in AWS right those are things that
are possible with def pod that's very
exciting project as well you'll find all
of that in our GitHub so just check out
our Loft dsh GitHub and you'll see all
the repositories there there's quite a
few more than than the couple ones I
just mentioned Death part and cluster we
will put that all in the show notes now
we at end of time Lucas I want to thank
you for joining software engineering
radio
thank you so much for having me this was
fun this has been Robert bluman and
thank you for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by it e software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website atr.com
[Music]
you can also email us at team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under creative
comments license
2.5 thanks for listening